Guide to the Bob Nelkin Collection of ACC-PARC Records, 1953-2000 MSS 1002
Heinz History Center
- State School and Hospital (SSH) and Interim Care Committee Records, 1972-1997; II.
  - Western State School and Hospital (WSSH), 1967-1984; 2.
    - Meeting with Coroner Jackson: Minutes, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Construction/Expansion Records, 1973-1976 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Liaison Committee Meeting Minutes Regarding Dental Care, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 48)
      - Western State School and Hospital Liaison Committee Meeting Minutes (2), September 25, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 48, Item 1)
        Minutes from the Western State School and Hospital Liaison Committee September 25, 1975, meeting. In this meeting, the committee questioned Dr. Craig Mulvihill, WSSH's dentist, about the quality of dental care provided at the institution.
      - Western State School and Hospital Liaison Committee Meeting Minutes (3), April 24, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 48, Item 2)
        Minutes from the Western State School and Hospital Liaison Committee April 24, 1975, meeting following a disturbance at the school caused by a resident.
    - 406 Intervention Team Minutes, 1975-1978 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Act 75A Implementation Records, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Right to Education Records I, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Right to Education Records II, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 52)
      - Letter from Frank S. Beal to Roger E. Buchanan, April 23, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 52, Item 1)
        A letter from Secretary Frank Beal to Robert Buchanan and the rest of the Right to Education Committee. Beal responds to the committee's concerns regarding the construction of classroom "units" at Ebensburg State School, which they worry will provide permanent, and unsatisfactory education to students who would benefit from an integrated classroom setting.
      - Letter from Harry Herman to Frank Beal, April 17, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 52, Item 2)
        A letter from Harry Herman, superintendent of Ebensburg State School and Hospital, to Frank Beal regarding the proposed modular education units at Ebensburg. Herman states that the units are for the education of students who are possible candidates for community placement.
      - Letter from Robert Buchanan to Judge Alexander Barbieri, April 21, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 52, Item 3)
        A letter from Roger Buchanan to Judge Alexander Barbieri clarifying PARC's views on a variety of subjects as they relate to the residents of Pennsylvania state schools.
      - Letter from Roger Buchanan to F. John Hagele, April 21, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 52, Item 4)
        A letter from Roger Buchanan to F. John Hagele of Pepper, Hamilton & Scheetz regarding the Pennsylvania Department of Education's failure to ensure education for all citizens with developmental and intellectual disabilities.
      - Demountable Classrooms Planned for White Haven and Hamburg State Schools and Hospitals Memo, April 17, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 52, Item 5)
        A memo from Roger Buchanan to PARC Chapter Executives and the Right to Education Committee members. Buchanan views the creation of these classrooms as an expansion of institutionalization and Pennsylvania's failure to educate students with developmental and intellectual disabilities.
      - Letter from Roger Buchanan to Frank S. Beal, April 4, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 52, Item 6)
        A letter from Roger Buchanan on behalf of PARC's Right to Education Committee to Frank S Beal regarding the planned modular education units for Ebensburg State School and Hospital. While PARC applauds superintendent Herman on attempts to increase educational programs for individuals over 21 years of age, PARC is concerned that these units will be permanent rather than transitional.
      - Letter from Bob Nelkin to Joe McKenna, March 21, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 52, Item 7)
        A letter from Bob Nelkin to Joe McKenna, a supervisor at Western State School and Hospital, objecting to the punishment of Howard P. Howard was punished for truancy by being placed in a wing with severely disabled individuals.
      - Letter to Joseph McKenna Regarding Kim V., January 14, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 52, Item 8)
        A letter from Mrs. M. to Joseph McKenna, a supervisor at Western State School and Hospital, regarding the health and rehabilitation of Kim V., her daughter.
      - Letter from Virginia Thornburgh to Donald Carroll Regarding Education at Western State School and Hospital, October 8, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 52, Item 9)
        A letter from Virginia Thornburgh to Donald M. Carroll, the Commissioner for Basic Education for the Pennsylvania Department of Education, expressing concern over the removal of the Department of Public Welfare staff from Western State School and Hospital and the need to reinstate an educational program at Intermediate Unit #1 at WSSH.
      - Immediate Needs for Intermediate Unit 1 at Western State School and Hospital, November 5, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 52, Item 10)
        A list of needs at Western State School and Hospital's Intermediate Unit #1 for the 1974-1975 school year to provide adequate educational services for the residents of I.U. #1.
    - Article: Death is "A Way of Life" I, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Article: Death is "A Way of Life" II, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 54)
      - Pittsburgh Magazine "Behind the Walls" Article, October 1975 (Box 3, Folder 54, Item 1)
        A scan of the cover page for the October 1975 edition of the Pittsburgh Magazine with a feature story titled "Behind the Walls" on the life of residents, accidents, and death at Western State School and Hospital.
    - Volunteer Recognition Programs, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - News Clipping Advocacy Efforts (WSSH and Highland Park), 1967-1984 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - News Clipping Advocacy Efforts (Highland Park and WSSH), 1972-1975 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - News Clippings, 1974-1976 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - News Clippings, November 1974 - August 1978, 1974-1978 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Bob Nelkin Award Regarding Advocacy for Residents of WSSH, 1975-1978 (Box 3, Folder 60)
      - "Fund Hike Sought: Retarded Facilities Hit" Article, 1974-11-19 (Box 3, Folder 60, Item 1)
        A scan of the "Fund Hike Sought: Retarded Facilities Hit" article in the Beaver County Times newspaper. The article discusses PARC's request to increase funding for state schools and hospitals by $12.6 million to improve conditions and staffing.
    - Maltreatment and Deaths - Civil Suit Records, 1974-1978 (Box 3, Folder 61)
      - Letter from ACLU Pittsburgh to Aldo Colautti Regarding Howard P., August 2, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 61, Item 1)
        A letter from the ACLU Pittsburgh to Aldo Colautti, secretary of the Department of Public Welfare. The ACLU condemns the treatment of Howard P., who was placed in solitary confinement at Western State School and Hospital for over one month after breaking the leg of another resident.
      - "Understanding Death at State Institutions" Letter, November 15, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 61, Item 2)
        A letter sent to state legislators informing them of a seminar titled "Understanding Death at State Institutions" at Western State School and Hospital. The seminar, sponsored by both ACC-PARC and WSSH Parent's Group, aimed to educate legislators about the conditions that led to deaths at state institutions.
      - Deaths at State School Letter, January 13, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 61, Item 3)
        A letter from Deputy Secretary for Mental Retardation Stanley Meyers to L. Steuart Brown of PARC regarding the deaths at state institutions between July 1, 1973, and June 30, 1974.
      - ACC-PARC News Release Regarding the Death of Paul Jenkins, November 14, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 61, Item 4)
        An ACC-PARC news release following the death of Paul Jenkins at Western State School and Hospital.
      - "Walking with Spirit of Christmas" Article, December 23, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 61, Item 5)
        A copy of the "Walking with Spirit of Christmas" article in McKeesport's The Daily News newspaper regarding Joyce Z. and her adoptive mother, Nancy Tassone.
    - Vecchione Court Decision Records, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Report: Confidential Medical Task Force, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Polk Center, c1966-1997; 3.
    This subseries is comprised of records that document the ongoing efforts of ACC-PARC members to investigate the living conditions of people with disabilities at the Polk Center. Internal policy documents, case files, reports, correspondence, visitation team records, press releases, Polk newsletters, and news clippings. The reports in this subseries shed light on living conditions at the Polk Center and originate from both internal and external sources, including the Polk superintendent, ACC-PARC members, and the American Association of Mental Deficiency. Correspondence in this subseries documents Bob Nelkin and the ACC-PARC's efforts to expose understaffing and inadequate living conditions at the Polk Center. These conditions included the use of cages and restraints. Also documented in the correspondence are investigations into resident deaths at Polk.
    Worthy of note are an aggregate of correspondence received by Helene Wohlgemuth, secretary of the Department of Public Welfare, in response to her decision to fire Dr. James McClelland from his position as superintendent of the Polk Center (1973-1976). In addition to Wohlgemuth's decision, correspondents also often addressed their stance on the use of cages in their letters. Wohlgemuth gave these files to Bob Nelkin. Also included in this subseries is a copy of the notification letter sent to Dr. McClelland as well as a report of conditions following his dismissal.
    - Map of Grounds, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Policy Documents, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Review and Implementation of Policies at Polk State School Memo, November 19, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 2, Item 1)
        A memo from Joseph Colombatto to department heads of Polk State School and Hospital. Colombatto informs the department heads of the newly established Policy Review Committee and how that affects the employees of the institution.
      - Polk State School and Hospital General Statement of Policies and Procedures, November 19, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 2, Item 2)
        The General Statement of Policy of Polk State School and Hospital. This statement stresses the rights of residents and the need to eliminate harmful or damaging attitudes towards residents.
      - Polk State School and Hospital Admission Policies and Procedures, October 19, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 2, Item 3)
        The admissions policies and procedures for Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Polk State School and Hospital Policy on Abusive Treatment of Residents, November 19, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 2, Item 4)
        Polk State School and Hospital's policy regarding the abusive treatment of residents. This policy condemns both the physical and psychological abuse of residents by staff.
      - Polk State School and Hospital Policies on Resident Communications, November 19, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 2, Item 5)
        Polk State School and Hospital's policies on resident communications, including letter-writing and telephone communications.
    - Self-Evaluation Reports - American Association of Mental Deficiency (AAMD) Institutional Evaluation Projects, 1966-1969 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Final Report: American Association on Mental Deficiency, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Work Plan Program, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Superintendent's Reports, July-August 1972 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Superintendent's Reports, October-December 1972 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Superintendent's Reports, January-February 1973 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Meeting with Dr. McClelland, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - ACC-PARC Meeting with Dr. James McClelland Minutes, April 2, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 9, Item 1)
        Minutes from a meeting between ACC-PARC members and Dr. James McClelland, superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital. One of the topics discussed included the dispersal of Polk residents.
    - Visitation Reports and Notes, 1972-1976 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - ACC-PARC Residential Care Committee Polk State School and Hospital Visit Report, October 11, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 10, Item 1)
        A report detailing the October 11, 1973 visit to Polk State School and Hospital by Virginia Thornburgh, Jean Isherwood, and Bob Nelkin.
      - Polk State School and Hospital Visit Report, January 17, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 10, Item 2)
        A report detailing the January 17, 1975 visit to Polk State School and Hospital by Sally Hollyfield, Doug Spencer, Midge Scannell, Virginia Thornburg, Anne Winkler, and Jean Isherwood.
      - Polk State School and Hospital Visit Report (2), May 25, 1973 - August 23, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 10, Item 3)
        Letters from Marlene Burda, chairwoman of PARC Residential Services Committee, and Elsie Schmidt, PARC president, to Secretaries Anna Belle Calloway and Frank S. Beal, and Polk State School and Hospital Superintendent Nicholas D'Aluisio presenting copies of PARC's report following the May 25, 1976 visit to Polk State School and Hospital. A copy of PARC's report accompanies these letters.
      - ACC-PARC Residential Care Committee Polk State School and Hospital Visit Report (2), March 7, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 10, Item 4)
        ACC-PARC Residential Care Committee's report detailing the March 7, 1974 visit to Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Gardenside Building Concerns, December 11, 1973 - January 10, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 10, Item 5)
        A letter from Virginia Thornburgh, chairwoman of the Residential Care Committee, to Joseph Colombatto of Polk State School and Hospital regarding the committee's December 11, 1973 visit to the institution. A copy of the Residential Care Committee's report detailing the December 1973 visit to Polk State School and the concerns they had regarding the Polk's Gardenside Building accompanies the letter.
    - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Follow Up Letter from E. Gene Patterson to Robert Haigh, May 11, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 11, Item 1)
        A letter from E. Gene Patterson of NARC to Robert Haigh of the Department of Public Welfare reflecting on the recent visit to Polk State School and Hospital. Patterson focuses on Polk's need to establish goals and to move away from the medical model.
      - Letter from Wolf Wolfensberger to Mel Knowlton, May 7, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 11, Item 2)
        A letter from Wolf Wolfensberger to Mel Knowlton commending the actions of Helene Wohlgemuth. Wolfensberger delves into the psychology of caging and the McClelland apologists.
      - Polk State School and Hospital Admission Policies and Procedures Letter, October 17, 1973 - November 2, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 11, Item 3)
        A letter from Joseph Colombatto, superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital, to Dr. Norman Mulgrave, ACC-PARC president, regarding the admissions policies at Polk. Colombatto included a draft of proposed policies with his letter.
      - Polk State School Union Grievance Letter, December 27, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 11, Item 4)
        A letter denying the Polk State School and Hospital Child Care Aides' grievance regarding unannounced parental visits and parents dressing and undressing their children.
      - Letter from Joseph Colombatto to Richard Sell Regarding Polk State School and Hospital Right to Education, October 30, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 11, Item 5)
        A letter from Joseph Colombatto, superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital, to Richard Sell of ACC-PARC responding to Sell's questions regarding the Polk-Right to Education lawsuit.
      - Letter from Joseph Colombatto and John Bower to Parents of Polk State School and Hospital Residents, August 30, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 11, Item 6)
        A letter from Joseph Colombatto and John Bower of Polk State School and Hospital to parents of residents. This letter informs parents of their child's placement in an educational program created as a result of the Right to Education Consent Agreement.
      - Parent Allegations Against Polk State School and Hospital, October 3, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 11, Item 7)
        A letter from Bob Nelkin to Polk State School and Hospital Superintendent, Joseph Colombatto, inquiring about recent allegations made by a parent of a resident. Allegations include the placement of a resident made regardless of handicap degree, misleading information from the Department of Public Welfare, and a lack of alternatives to cages that have resulted in injuries.
      - "Mass Bar-Bat Mitzvah for Retarded Slated" Article, October 23, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 11, Item 8)
        A copy of the "Mass Bar-Bat Mitzvah for Retarded Slated" article in the Jewish Chronicle of Pittsburgh newspaper describing a mass bar-bat mitzvah event for residents of Polk, Wester, Cresson, and Ebensburg state school and hospitals.
      - Mrs. Weikers "Call of Hope" Volunteering Response, June 1973 (Box 4, Folder 11, Item 9)
        A scan of Mrs. Weikers' return card for volunteering for ACC-PARC's "Call of Hope" event. Weikers declines to volunteer on the belief that ACC-PARC was partly responsible for the dismissal of Dr. McClelland as Polk State School and Hospital Superintendent.
      - Letter from Barbara Sistik to Governor Milton Shapp Requesting Visit to Polk State School and Hospital, March 7, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 11, Item 10)
        A letter from Barbara Sistik to Governor Milton J Shapp requesting him to make an unannounced visit Polk State School and Hospital. Sistik reminds Shapp of his promise to visit the institution that he made as a guest on Mike Levine's Show on KDKA.
      - Letter from Arthur Bolton to Richard Loring Regarding the Polk Dispersal Project, February 16, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 11, Item 11)
        A letter from Arthur Bolton to Richard Long regarding how the MH/MR Office can aid in the dispersal of Polk State School and Hospital. Bolton aims to create opportunities in communities for Polk residents and staff during and after deinstitutionalizing to be used as a model for future dispersal projects at other institutions.
    - Right to Communication Correspondence, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - Letter from Norman Taylor to Dr. James McClelland Regarding Rights of Residents to Outside Written and Telephone Communications, February 9, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 12, Item 1)
        A letter from Norman Taylor to Polk State School and Hospital Superintendent, Dr. James McClelland, criticizing Polk's practice of censoring outside mail and prohibiting residents from making or receiving telephone calls.
      - Letter from Mr. W. to Dr. James H. McClelland, February 6, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 12, Item 2)
        A letter from Herbert W. responding to Dr. McClelland's offer to make an exception to Polk State School and Hospital's communication policy for his daughter, Nancy. Mr. W. informs McClelland of his contact with Mike Levine, the host of a KDKA program, and his plan to cooperate with Levine until free communication is available to all Polk residents.
      - Letter from Mike Levine to Norman Taylor, c. 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 12, Item 3)
        A letter from Mike Levine, the host of a program on KDKA, to Norman Taylor of the Department of Public Welfare. Levine expresses frustration at the communication policies at Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Dr. James McClelland to Mr. W., January 8, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 12, Item 4)
        A letter from Dr. James H. McClelland, superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital, to Herbert W., a parent of a Polk resident. McClelland addresses the issue of telephone communications with Nancy W., Mr. W.'s daughter, and resident communications in general. McClelland makes an exception for Nancy but says he can not make any promises about access for all Polk residents.
      - Letter from Mr. W. to Mike Levine, January 24, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 12, Item 5)
        A letter from Herbert W. to KDKA host Mike Levine. Mr. W. updates Levine on his correspondence with Dr. McClelland. Mr. W. also agrees that this communication issue may be a worthwhile project for ACC-PARC.
      - Letter from Mike Levine to Mr. W., October 26, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 12, Item 6)
        A letter from Mike Levine, a host of a KDKA program, to Herbert W. W., a parent of a Polk State School and Hospital resident, regarding Mr. W.'s difficulty communicating with his daughter, Nancy.
      - Letter from Mr. W. to Mike Levine (2), October 20, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 12, Item 7)
        A letter from Herbert W. W. to KDKA host Mike Levine. Mr. W. tells Levine of the difficulties he has contacting his daughter Nancy, a Polk State School and Hospital resident.
      - Letter from Charles Peters to Norman Taylor, November 15, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 12, Item 8)
        A letter from Charles Peters, executive director of ACC-PARC, to Secretary Norman Taylor expressing his support for Mr. W. and Mike Levine's demands regarding telephone access for residents of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Mike Levine to Dr. Norman Mulgrave, October 26, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 12, Item 9)
        A letter from Mike Levine, a host of a KDKA program, to Dr. Norman Mulgrave of ACC-PARC, bringing awareness to Herbert W.'s complaint regarding resident communications at Polk State School and Hospital.
    - DPW: Helene Wohlgemuth Regarding Raymond H. Case File, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Death of Raymond Helman Report, October 24, 1972 - December 7, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 13, Item 1)
        A collection of memos, notes, and reports related to the death of Raymond Helman, a resident of Polk State School and Hospital.
    - DPW: Helene Wohlgemuth Correspondence to Dr. McClelland Regarding Firing, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - Dr. James McClelland Removal Letter, April 16, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 14, Item 1)
        A letter from Helene Wohlgemuth to Dr. James McClelland removing him from his position as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Polk Superintendent Fired Summary, April 1973 (Box 4, Folder 14, Item 2)
        A summary of the events surrounding the Helene Wohlgemuth's visit to Polk State School and Hospital and the removal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent.
      - Helene Wohlgemuth Memo to State Institution Superintendents, May 9, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 14, Item 3)
        A memo from Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth to the superintendents of state institutions and regional deputy secretaries prohibiting the use of cages and pens at state institutions.
    - DPW Press Releases, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - Department of Public Welfare News Release Regarding Polk State School and Hospital, May 9, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 15, Item 1)
        The Department of Public Welfare's news release regarding the special visitation teams at Polk State School and Hospital. These teams included national specialists and policy-makers and aimed at improving programming and resident care.
      - Program Review Starts at Eastern State School and Hospital and Four Other Institutions News Release, May 20, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 15, Item 2)
        The Department of Public Welfare's news release regarding a planned review of Eastern State School and Hospital and four other programs in the Philadelphia area. The purpose of these reviews was to study programming deficiencies and set goals for these institutions.
      - Institution Review to Four More Facilities News Release, July 10, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 15, Item 3)
        The Department of Public Welfare's news release regarding the department's expansion of institutional reviews to other state institutions
    - Correspondence Regarding Cages at Polk, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - DPW: Helene Wohlgemuth Regarding Cages at Polk Center Correspondence I, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17)